<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to Friends coming forth in the beginning of a testimony and of the snares of the enemy therein.</title>
            <author>Marshall, Charles, 1637-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680-1730</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M739A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC T93380</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896308</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2395:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to Friends coming forth in the beginning of a testimony and of the snares of the enemy therein.</title>
                  <author>Marshall, Charles, 1637-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?,</pubPlace>
                  <date>1730?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Charles Marshall.</note>
                  <note>Drop-head title.</note>
                  <note>Wing (CD-ROM edition) reports date of publication as 1680.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Worship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->
            <head>AN EPISTLE TO FRIENDS Coming forth in the Beginning of a TESTIMONY: And of the Snares of the Enemy therein.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly beloved Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHO in your Meetings and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies ſometimes feel the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of a Teſtimony for the Lord, ſpring and move in your Hearts; keep your Watch in the Light, that ſo none
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154061:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->ſtay behind, neither run before, but let all who open their Mouths in the Aſſemblies of the Lord's People, do it as the Oracles of God, in the Ariſing of the eternal pure Power; for nothing can beget to God, but what comes from the immortal Word of Life, that lives and abides for ever; and nothing can refreſh, ſtrengthen or comfort that which is begotten by the immortal Word of Life, but what ſprings from the ſame. And therefore, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> whom this concerns, wait dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, not only to know and ſavour every Motion, but alſo to know the appointed Time and Seaſon when the ſame Motion ſhould be brought forth; ſo ſhall what is miniſtred, if it be but few Words, reach to the Witneſs, and do its Service. For this I have learned, That though there may be a true Motion of the Power of the Lord, and a true Operation thereof, yet where there is not a true waiting for the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154061:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->perfecting of what is to be brought forth, but inſtead thereof, it coming forth before the Time, that which is brought forth ſeems an untimely Birth; which is hurt as to the Veſſel through which it comes, and the Hearers thereof are burthened, and the Life which firſt moved comes to be oppreſſed; and here is the Ground of that untimely Birth that never ſaw the Sun, that hath, doth, or ſhall come forth: And as long as any are found walking in this By-path, although they may find the true Power of God moving in them, yet they never come to be ſkilful, nor to divide the Word of God aright; and ſuch do not truly grow, but ſometimes bring forth a Mixture, ſowing the Field with two Sorts of Grain, and wearing a Linen and Woollen Garment.</p>
            <p>So, <hi>Friends,</hi> this lieth upon my Spirit to all who feel the Beginning of a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154061:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->ſpring in your Hearts; Wait dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently in that Light, low, in the pure Stilneſs and Paſſiveneſs of your Spirits; and as you here wait, you will come to feel the Counſel of the Lord ſealed unto your Underſtandings, and ſee the Time when to ſpeak, and when to be ſilent; and here will be a right and true Increaſe of your Teſtimonies: And when that which is thus ſealed to the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is offered, retire inward, and ſink down into the pure Stilneſs, and keep in the Valley; and let all know, that no Miniſtration, ſave that which comes from Life itſelf, from the freſh Ariſings of the pure Power of the Lord, availeth any Thing; and all Miniſtrings out of this will come to an End, and fade, and vaniſh in the approaching Day of Trial.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> as the Mind and Will of the Lord is made manifeſt, yield
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154061:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->ſincere Obedience thereunto, if the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirings be but a few Words; for I have ſeen it a dangerous Thing to reſiſt and rebel againſt the Motions of God's Power, and have known many Hours of Sorrow for ſo rebelling. And in the Day of a beginning of a Teſtimony for the Lord, even in the upright Heart, great will be the Oppoſition of the Enemy every Way, where he cannot lead out before, for to bring forth an untimely Birth; there he will endeavour to ſhut up the Heart in Diſobedience, or Rebellion, or raiſe up ſo many Fears, Doubts and Amazements, if poſſible to bewilder the Soul: And here I had periſhed, if it had not been for the dear Love and tender Mercy of the Lord. And ſo, <hi>dear Friends,</hi> for whoſe Sake I am moved thus to write, when a Motion is felt, and Openings are in the Heart, and the Power of the Lord is prevailing, then ſink down in that in which no vain
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154061:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->Thought can be hid, and ſtand ſingle and paſſive; and the more ſtill, humble and paſſive thou art, who art thus exerciſed, the Motion of Life will the more live and ſhew itſelf, and the Power will ariſe and clear thy Underſtanding; and then, in the Power which warmeth thy Heart, and moveth on thy Spirit, enter into thy Service; and when that's done, add not, but ſit in the ſtill Habitation, and in that Humility and Paſſiveneſs thou waſt in before, and then the Reward of Obedience thou wilt feel, and grow in Experience and Knowledge, and be more and more furniſhed to every good Word and Work.</p>
            <p>And in this even Path, in which all will feel a being ſtrengthened with Might in the inward Man, and furniſhed to ſerve the Lord, God Almighty preſerve all that are thus exerciſed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154061:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
And, <hi>Friends,</hi> when any through want of Experience err, in running before the Power, be very tender; and altho' there may be a Savour and Judgment in your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and you may be burthened, yet beware how you ſpeak to eaſe yourſelves, but wait on the Lord therein, to be guided by his Counſel; for ſome having ſuch a Senſe, as aforeſaid, and not having a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning wherein the Miſcarriage lay, have run forth in Judgment, and ſo have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hurt, and even deſtroyed, or at leaſt have become a Stumbling-block to ſuch an exerciſed Friend, and have alſo much hurt themſelves; ſo that they not having a true Diſcerning, between the firſt moving Cauſe, which is the Power, and that which led forth before the Power, have judged both, and ſo have brought a Hurt over their own Souls, through judging the Power of the Lord; and this ſometimes may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to hurt others: Out of which Snare
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154061:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->God Almighty preſerve all, that ſo one may be a Strength to another, taking one another by the Hand, ſaying one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Let us go up to the Mountain of the Lord, to the Houſe of the God of</hi> Jacob, who will teach us more and more of his Ways; and here, in all God's holy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, is neither hurting nor deſtroying.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given forth in the Moving of God's eternal Spirit, through your dear Brother,</dateline> 
               <signed>CHARLES MARSHALL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
